<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Exercise on Magnus Ross</title>
    <link>/tags/exercise/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Exercise on Magnus Ross</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/exercise/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Expectation maximization for mixture of linear experts</title>
      <link>/posts/em_problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/em_problem/</guid>
      <description>The EM algorithm for me is one of those things that I feel I should know back to front, since it&amp;rsquo;s a pretty foundational algorithm in probabilistic ML. Unfortunately though I&amp;rsquo;ve never actually used it explicitly in a model I have built, despite reading about it in various textbooks, so I never properly got to grips with it. If you feel the same way, then hopefully this question will help. It&amp;rsquo;s from the new Murphy book, which is a fantastic reference.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distributions of quotients of uniform RVs</title>
      <link>/posts/rvquotients_problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/rvquotients_problem/</guid>
      <description>This is a nice problem from the book &amp;ldquo;Cut the knot&amp;rdquo;, which is a compilation of probability riddles and brain teasers. I like the book because many of the problems are about intuitive reasoning, and don&amp;rsquo;t really involve that much technical knowledge of probability theory, so they can be fun to do with people who don&amp;rsquo;t have a formal maths background. Each problem can also generally be solved many different ways, so it&amp;rsquo;s fun to compare solutions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mercer theorem measure and RKHS norm</title>
      <link>/posts/mercerrkhs_problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/mercerrkhs_problem/</guid>
      <description>This problem from the GPML book relates to the effect of the choice of measure when using Mercer&amp;rsquo;s theorem to compute kernel eigenfunctions on the resulting norm in the RKHS induced by that kernel. In the problem we show that in the finite dimensional case (this also applies in the ( \infty ) dimensions case but it is then harder to show), the RKHS norm is independent of the measure chosen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Converting state misalignment in probabilistic numeric ODE solver to SDE.</title>
      <link>/posts/pn_solver_problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/pn_solver_problem/</guid>
      <description>It is only the third week and I have already failed to manage my goal of posting one solution per week, not a good sign for the future&amp;hellip; In my defense, I was busy last week attending the Probabilistic Numerics Spring School, at which I learned lots about probabilistic ODE solvers, on which this weeks late question is based.
Probabilistic ODE solvers work by placing a Markovian GP prior (usually the ( q )-times integrated Wiener process) over the solution, given this prior, we then condition on the fact samples of this GP must solve the ODE at a given set of time steps, that is to say the derivatives of the GP prior must match the derivative function of the ODE.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Relationship between the Frobenius norm and singular values in SVD</title>
      <link>/posts/frobeniusnorm_problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/frobeniusnorm_problem/</guid>
      <description>Problem
Note: I was brushing up on my SVD using the brilliant &amp;ldquo;Mathematics for Machine Learning&amp;rdquo; book, but the exercises listed in the book for SVD were a bit basic, so I decided to try use ChatGPT to generate a question. The problem below is what came out, quite impressive, although there were quite a few errors in the question that I had to fix (e.g the dimensionalities of the matrices).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Winners curse in Bayesian optimisation</title>
      <link>/posts/winnerscurse_problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/winnerscurse_problem/</guid>
      <description>Problem
Take an objective function ( f(x) ) with GP prior and i.i.d. Gaussian noise with variance ( \sigma^2 ), so ( y_i = f(x_i) + \epsilon_i ) with ( \epsilon_i \sim \mathcal{N}(0, \sigma^2) ). Assume two locations ( x_1, x_2 ) are sufficiently separated that their function values ( f(x_1) ) and ( f(x_2) ) are independent. Compute the posterior ( p(\epsilon_1-\epsilon_2|y_1, y_2) ) and use it to justify that the expected improvement in Bayesian optimisation suffers winners curse for a noisy objective.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
